So, for Notion, we think a lot about
like primitives or building blocks. Our
goal as a company is to
try to break the pattern of these like
rigid vertical SaaS
tools and instead reconstruct them from
their underlying primitives and allow
users to make their own custom software.
So, things like like a relational
database or
a table view or different blocks within
a page. I think of AI is another
primitive in the toolbox. Let's you do
really useful automations on top.
So, yeah, we have AI primitive concepts.
So, the writing that AI autofill is a
great example. That's a primitive where
you can write a custom prompt and it can
do whatever you want.
You're listening to the AI Native Dev,
brought to you by Tesla.
Hello everyone. Welcome back to the AI
Native Dev. Today we have an opportunity
to talk to one of the makers of probably
one of the most advanced AI adopters in
the industry right now, which is Simon
Last, the co-founder of Notion. Simon,
thanks for coming on to the show.
Hey Guy, really happy to be here.
Simon, there's a lot for us to cover,
but I'm thankful that you're joining
because I really perceive Notion as one
of the pioneers in the product side of
making AI really a a fundamental part of
the of the product and in in useful
ways, but also some ways that feel like
a little bit weird and experimental,
which I love. Like I like that it's a a
bit of a combo of the two. And in the
spirit of sharing and learning as a
community, it's great to just tap a
little bit to the do's and don'ts and
the learnings and perspectives that you
might have accumulated in the process.
So, I guess before we dive into the
specific questions and try to tie them
in and understand how it relates to
software development, tell us a little
bit about what Notion AI is. I I think
people will be well familiar with Notion
as a modern knowledge base for the
organization, but tell us a bit about
Notion AI.
Yeah, so
we got started working on it. It was
back in October 2022. We had just gotten
early access to GPT-4, and it was
something that I've been uh closely
watching for a while, and then playing
with GPT-4 was the trigger for me. Oh my
god, this thing is actually really
useful now. Has a bunch more world
knowledge. It can actually like follow
complex instructions. Oh, we immediately
got to work then on building our first
product, which is a AI writing
assistant, and we launched that in
February '23.
So, basically, I can write and edit
text, insert new content, and and then
there's a bunch of pre-packaged prompts
for for different common actions like
improving your writing.
Yeah,
and this one was focused on sort of
inline creation or more like it was
always with some command, right? With
sort of a a slash.
Well, yeah, so there were pre-packaged
actions, and then also you could just
type whatever you wanted. So,
similar to the combo I guess that we're
seeing today as well with sort of the
code completion and chat interfaces that
we see in cursor or any coding tool.
Yeah, it's still in the product today.
It's very similar to the cursor inline
replace or insert. And then the second
product that we worked on we call AI
autofill, and it's basically you give
the AI
a prompt on on an entire column of a
database, and then it will like fill out
it for all the rows for all that column.
So, you can fill out a summary, you
could do like a translation of a
different column, they could extract
some information from the document.
Something like that.
That was pretty useful.
And then the third product that we
shipped in November '23 was Q&A. So,
basically, we built an embedding index
over all of Notion, and then you could
ask questions and it's a chatbot.
That one took us a bit longer just cuz
there's obviously a lot more technical
stuff involved around indexing all of
Notion, especially at our scale. There's
a lot of data, and then figuring out
like the how to retrieve it and answer
from it.
And then
I'm a big fan of the column capabilities
of it. Used quite heavily in Tessal in a
variety of spots as a as a summarizer of
it. Go on. Sorry about interrupting you.
So, third product and
So, the third product, yeah. And then
since then throughout 2024, we've been
working on what we call AI connectors.
So, indexing not just Notion, but
external apps and evolving Q&A to be
like a a true universal search product.
And then we've also been adding more
capabilities to the the chatbot to turn
into more like an assistant. So, it can
now create and edit pages. And they can
do all of this using retrieval. So, you
can do something like go find me
information about this customer and then
draft me a customer proposal and it'll
fill it out in the right format.
So, those are our kind of actions that
complement the search and they're again
kind of Notion-wide as opposed to
something specific. And I'm curious
organizationally like you describe these
as different products who you call them.
They're clearly a user experience as a
them as a as capabilities within the
product within maybe the sort of the one
experience that is Notion. How did you
organize for this? I guess both when the
penny dropped or when you got that
exposure is it kind of a commando force
that sort of put to the side to tackle
it or not? And also as you evolve are
these still dedicated teams outside the
main perimeter?
Yeah. So, I'm a big fan of starting like
a tiger team for a new initiative. I
think it's good to have like small group
of people that can move really fast and
have a clear focus mandate. So, that's
how it started and that's
how it was until probably
the launch of the original writer then
we created a more formal team around it
with a manager and
over the course of the past
year and a half we've been
growing the team. It's probably about 20
people now. And there's different kind
of like sub groups. There's the whole
group working on the the kind of
indexing ingestion
infrastructure. We have a group focused
on UX and a group focused on the
modeling
eval aspects. So, it's still mostly
centralized although we've been trying
to democratize it a little bit. So, we
want more teams to be using AI. I don't
know. I just think there's so much
low-hanging fruit. I can think of a new
idea every day and be like, "Oh,
I wish somebody would work on that." It
feels like this crazy technology just
dropped upon us and it can do all these
like insane things if you have the idea
and you know how to iterate on it. So,
yeah, we
we're trying to democratize a little bit
more.
We have two or three other teams also
working on AI stuff now. Uh there's been
some challenges with that, which we can
chat about if you want.
Yeah, I'm very curious to dive in cuz
indeed some things are the same and you
just want to tap into them and some
things are are quite substantially
different. But I guess still on the
organization, do you think about the
team that is originally building it as a
platform team? How did you consider that
division now that you've been building
this for a couple of years and you have
it sounds like multiple teams working at
How do you think about the shared
infrastructure, if you will, between
those or the shared learnings or
evaluation methods as we'll touch on in
a sec? How do you think about I guess
enabling these other teams to adopt AI
more easily?
Yeah, that's a good question. Yeah,
initially we didn't think of it that
way. It was more just like a end-to-end
product team. The only goal was just to
Just ship things.
Yeah, just just ship beautiful stuff and
then we're learning along the way how to
do evals. And then our goal is to make
it more of a platform team. So, we're
trying to take what we build and expose
it as
something reproducible. I would say it's
actually pretty tricky because in many
ways we don't really do any training of
models. It's all about taking the best
models out there and packaging them into
the product and making everything work
well, which involves doing logging in
the right way. Like setting up your
prompt, doing logging in the right way,
doing evals, all that stuff. And it's
interesting. Most of it is actually
there's not that much technically
challenging, I would say, about the
platform aspect. A lot of it is more
about the best practice of how you do it
and the knowledge of
what steps you take and even how to
think about it. Yeah, it it's a tricky
thing to get other people to work on
without context. What we've had the
success with actually is when someone
new wants to work on AI, we've had a lot
of success with just having them join
the AI team temporarily, and then they
just join our stand-ups and get in the
weeds with us every day. And then,
quickly pick up all the context around
like how to do evals, how to
iterate on prompts, and yeah, we found
it challenging the other way, where we
just like give them like the code
pointers to all the different layers of
the stack.
Here's the thing that would run the
inference or whatever it is, but
Yeah, and the code isn't that
complicated. I would say the complexity
is actually more in like
the best practice of how you how you do
things, and and the mental model that
you would think about it.
Yeah. Yeah, I I think that makes perfect
sense. I actually had the Patrick
Dubois, who's a kind of DevOps luminary,
on the podcast, and we talked about how
the analogies work from the DevOps era,
and a lot of it is indeed about platform
teams and reuse, but also about
embedding and about someone's walking a
mile in your shoes a little bit and
learning both for empathy, as you might
get annoyed later on when the product
doesn't work quite as you want, but for
skill sharing, and in security, and
DevSecOps we use the same approach. I
think we're running out of letters we
can add into the DevSecOps
I think we need to find a new strategy
there, but I think the approaches
themselves are worth quite well. I love
that approach, and it makes perfect
sense to me. Maybe let's indeed I want
to talk a bit more about the skills and
those gaps, but maybe let's first
describe these what has been repeated
often times in and this probably said
most succinctly by Des at Intercom in an
early episode here is that it's really
hard to know whether your product works
when you're building on the AI. So, I
guess what is your experience been when
you're building these capabilities? How
do you think about the evaluation, about
testing, and about whether it hit a
threshold, but also knowing whether it
hasn't regressed?
Yeah, it's super hard. It's a really
different experience than the pre-AI
world. Most of my experience is in
building Notion, building products, and
it's been honestly really painful. It's
very exciting and fun, and like I'm
pretty obsessed with the new technology,
but it's very painful, and I often miss
the old world. In the old world, I could
have an idea, and it might take me
longer than I thought, but I could
definitely ship it. But, in the AI
world, I can often have an idea and then
and then be surprised that it that
didn't work in some some way I didn't
expect. I would say I guess the way I
think about it is it's a twofold
challenge of
one is for the situations that you test,
you need to make sure that those work
and they don't regress.
And then there's this nebulous space of
the things that you haven't even tested.
It and it can be arbitrary.
And then
filling enough of that space so that
that you're confident that it's going to
match the distribution of what users are
going to request enough that you're
reasonably confident. You can never like
like like fully match it. Yeah, I guess
the way I think about that is yeah, you
need like a repeatable system or engine
around this and the key pieces are
something like you need you need to set
up good logging such that interactions
can be called up again. If it fails in
some way, you can go look at that and
it's extremely important to be able to
exactly reproduce the the failure
situation. The log has to be an exact
reproduction of the error and then you
should be able to just rerun that
inference with the exact same input.
Right.
That's really important. If you can't do
that, you're totally screwed.
And that's pretty it's probably some
challenges like I fully relate to the
full logging even more so than in
regular instrumented systems. How do you
work around the kind of the privacy
concerns or some of the user data
concerns around that?
Yeah, so so we take that really
seriously. What we do is we have an
opt-in early access program.
So, when you use the scenario, we show
you this little little pop-up and the
default is no, but you can opt in to to
share data with us and we don't use it
for training. It's just for evaluation.
So, basically that allows us to see the
logs. Like if you thumbs down, we can
actually see the log with the input and
then we can add it to an eval data set
and we segregate out the prod data to
make sure that it's not contaminated
with other sources, but yeah, that's
been extremely helpful. Let people opt
in and our user base is large enough
that
even if a pretty small percentage opt
in, it's still quite a lot of data.
So, logging is one.
Yeah, so logging is one. So, yeah, I
would say the next step is around
collecting the failures into data sets.
That's pretty important. So, just like
organizing them in some reasonable way
such that for the given task, you have
some data set or data sets that are like
these are all the cases that we care
about and all the known previous
failures. And then uh the next bit is
being able to evaluate that a given
failure is still happening or not. And
that can be really hard. There's many
ways to do evals, I think about you can
have deterministic or non-deterministic
evals. Definitely best use a
deterministic when you can, and then you
can use like a model-graded eval when
not. For model-graded evals, then they
work best when it's as concrete and
specific as possible. I've seen people
fail a lot doing model-graded evals
when it's like too generic or the task
is too difficult. I think I said this in
the last one, but if your model-graded
eval is not like robustly easy for the
model, then you have to have an eval for
your eval, and you just created a like a
new stack of problems.
And if you need an infinite loop. So,
related to the the data piece, so the
data sounded like going further back,
you have to create a set of the test
cases for the things you want to work,
and then a set of cases for problematic
ones. I guess that's synthetic, that's
at the beginning while you build a
feature, and then you need to have
access to real-world scenarios, and you
curate out of that the data set of
failure cases with the proper user
permission like amidst the users that
opted in to uh help improve the system.
I guess do you accumulate over there
good cases as well? Does the data set
mostly grow in the negative sense of
don't do this or
is it the same one? Is it basically
things where you're like here's a
scenario, here's the correct, and here's
the incorrect answer?
I tend not to care about good cases that
much. I think the the main focus is on
cuz what's the actionable value of that?
Maybe it's nice to have a few of them
just as a sanity check, but but to me
the main goal is to collect concrete
regressions, and then fix them, and then
make sure that they stay fixed. And then
over time you're ratcheting up
all these things that you they used to
not work are now working and then you're
going to set aside things that continue
to work. And that's ideal. You'll often
find issues that you just can't really
fix. And so
that's the that's part of the day.
Yeah, we'll come back to that. That's
really interesting cuz your product
works at this percentage of
Yeah, models have limits. There's many
issues that we can fix. And we're not a
foundation model companies. It's like,
all right, we'll just wait till the next
model comes out. Hopefully it'll fix
this one. So you want some kind of
eval. It could be just like a like a
human grade eval. Although that can
that'll quickly get out of control. Then
the really key next thing is you need to
enter this loop where you find some new
regression, you add it to your data set,
then you change the prompt in some way,
then you rerun the examples in the data
set, and then you need to be able to
decide whether it's like better or
worse. And ideally that's as automated
as possible.
And then ship that change. And then this
just this constant loop of new example,
improve the prompt.
Improve the prompt. And I think on the
eval side, the notion is pretty open or
flexible in what you can do with it.
There are a lot of degrees of freedom of
it. It's easy to think about
non-deterministic evaluations that you
can have. Notion is you're looking at
text and unstructured data and the
likes. What's an example of a structured
evaluation
that you can do in a Notion AI
capability?
Yeah, a lot of them like anything to do
with the formatting the output in some
way. Maybe it's XML, maybe it's JSON.
That's ideal. I think about if you're
having some issue, the best way to solve
it is by solving it with a validator.
Make it so that the invalid output is
impossible by structuring the output in
some way where you can deterministically
say that the bad output isn't correct.
That's That's like the best way to solve
any problem.
And as easy way to to evaluate it.
Another deterministic eval that we use
all the time is I love using mini
classifiers as as part of the flow.
Classifiers are really great. I By
classifier I just mean some inference
that outputs like an enum, like like set
of possible values. Classifiers are
really great cuz they're really easy to
eval because the output
the result of the of the product's
activity. Like you classify the output
from the LLM.
No, actually it's part of the flow. So,
for example, one thing we need to do as
part of the the chat experience is
decide whether to search or not. Just as
an example. So, it's should I search or
not search? Like yes or no, basically.
There's other classifiers that have more
than two possible values, but yeah,
those are really great in large part
because they're so easy to evaluate.
Because you just have the discrete truth
output, and then you just compare the
actual versus expected. It's really
great for that reason. You can collect a
big data set, and you can get a score.
Yeah. And I guess what has been the
driver behind the choice not to
fine-tune? Or actually, you know what? I
I I might be jumping to conclusions
here. You said you're not training
foundation models of it. Do you find
yourself fine-tuning the model?
Yeah, so we've tried fine-tuning
extensively.
I've personally banged my head on it a
lot. I think I need to ask OpenAI, but I
feel like I'm
if not the highest, maybe like 99th
percentile, like number of fine-tunes
created. Yeah, we tried fine-tuning
quite a lot. I would say yeah, the big
issue with fine-tuning
is that you're making your job like 100
times harder, at least. Because I needed
to collect this whole data set. The
actual fine-tuning process can be
difficult, especially if you're using a
lot just a slower. You have to wait for
things to train.
And then it's really hard to debug
issues. You're basically like creating
this black box where any of your new
examples, as you do successful
fine-tuning runs, any new examples can
poison the entire data set. You can mess
up the model.
So, it really requires you to have
extremely good evaluations, and it's
really hard to debug issues. So, I've
had issues with fine-tuning where, you
know, I would I would literally would
spend weeks trying to figure out what
the problem was, and it's just extremely
hard. Yeah, I would say I'm honestly not
that bullish on companies outside of the
foundation model companies doing
fine-tuning. And if I like meet a
startup and they say they're doing fine
tuning, I I actually now think of that
as like a negative update.
It's a lack of experience. You buy into
the promise, but it doesn't actually
Yeah, it it sounds cool. It doesn't work
in the real world. And I got bit by this
this bug, too. Like it sounds so cool
and like I think as engineers we want to
have more control. We want to do a
technically cool thing.
Um you know, the technically like
powerful thing and I was totally
susceptible to that and it and it was
really fun to do it. Uh but I don't
know. I'm a huge fan of in-context
learning. Like it's going to get better.
Yeah, there's there's a lot of reasons
to do it. Another big reason not to
fine-tune is if you're not a foundation
model company, you really want to just
be using the best model
at any given time and the progress is so
fast. And so if someone does some work
now, there's a good chance it's going to
work in the near future. And if you're
fine-tuning, you're really just locking
yourself in uh to this
slow, complicated process that makes it
hard to update. In-context learning is
amazing because if there's a new model,
I can switch the next day.
And I guess in in that case, cuz that
was my next question is like how often
do you try different models and how
rigorous a testing process do you feel
is necessary to make that switch? Cuz
those are probably new features are new
features, you control the timeline. A
new model comes along, I guess you still
control the timeline of how quickly you
you roll it out. How do you think about
the tradeoff between wanting to tap into
the new hotness versus I don't know,
potentially slow or how confident do you
feel about hey, like the next one came
out, can I sort of slot that in and get
it out within the week?
Yeah, it's a good question. I would say
the speed at which you can do it is
really dependent on the quality of your
evals. How good are your evals? Like how
good are they at telling you confidently
that this change will improve the the
overall experience?
Yeah, I would say that's one of the
reasons why
evals are so important. Probably
changing prompts is more important than
changing models. That's going to happen
much more much more often. Um but I mean
the same evals work for both, right? Um
yeah, we try to yeah, we've You've
invested a lot in really making sure the
tools are right and and the levels are
are really good. But also I would say as
a product company,
I think it's pretty important not to be
just like
jerked around constantly by new models
coming out. I think it's important to
like
think about like
really understanding the task that you
uniquely really care about effort
product and your alpha should be really
deeply understanding the task and what
it means to produce a good result and
the product experience around that and
like watching new capabilities and
releasing them as they come out. I think
it's it's really about you and your
product and like thinking about the
models as like a means to an end to to
enable that. And very often a new model
like just it's like shiny and cool but
like maybe it just doesn't really get
you much benefit for the task that you
care about.
Yeah. And I guess is there an example of
distilling you mentioned a couple of
times now the importance of being super
crisp about what it is that you need
either what is it that you want for your
task and from the model for it or in the
evaluation of actually asking the model
for something very concrete?
Is there a like an evolution example of
hey when I when we started with feature
or product XYZ
in Notion we did this and then we we
learned that we have to trim it this way
that jumps to mind?
Are you asking about making the task
more specific?
Yeah I just I'm I guess I'm curious what
has been the real world experience as
you were building within Notion these
capabilities of a case where making it
more crisp or more succinct has yielded
better results.
Yeah. In general yeah like the model
doesn't know what you want until you
tell it and right yeah I think a big one
Q&A is probably a really big example.
Obviously you know in the
in our very first experiment, you know,
you just give it the search results and
then you tell it to produce an answer or
something like that. I think a big
evolution there is coming up with a more
specific
rubric which
just explains in detail what we care
about and what it means for answer to be
good in our product experience. And then
uh literally telling the model that
rubric in the prompt is yeah, yeah,
super helpful.
And I guess just to make sure where
everybody listening is aligned on it,
the search versus chat is really like
search is the more traditional search,
the search or knowledge base that Notion
has had
for quite a while. It probably involves
some amount of AI there as well for
ranking or at least some algorithmic
ranking within the find it.
we
Oh, we actually completely rebuilt that
stack for the Q&A. The key technical
unlock there is the embeddings. Our
previous core search stack is like like
elastic search and full-text fuzzy
search. It It doesn't really work if you
just use that and try to do Q&A. Maybe
it works, but yeah, the really magical
experience comes from
rebuilding your stack to use embeddings.
So, today when you say search, you mean
the two parts are both kind of LLM
inspired. One is embeddings where I pull
up the relevant records from the vector
database or and then subsequently
process those wisely knowing what it is
that a good answer looks like. To get
those results.
Yeah, yeah, that's the Notion AI like
the Q&A experience.
Got it. So, I guess let's talk a little
bit about the people building the stuff.
We've talked about the frustrations. So,
the
the new skills, how does that change, if
at all, the skill set of the individuals
building and you already spoken about
the fact that there's a learning and so
not a If you're just a software engineer
and you pick it up right now, it's going
to take some getting used to and you'll
need to change some of your ways. Does
it change anything around who would be
good at it? The traits you might be
looking for in a hire?
Yeah, that's a really good question. And
I think it it definitely does. Yeah, I
think of a few things. So, one is es-
especially on the more producty side, if
you looking for someone that's going to
be able to lead an AI product team, you
definitely need someone that's going to
be very okay with a lot of uncertainty
and really pushing to think through
every day, are we doing the right thing?
I think that's yeah, it's so important
because you can use I've basically every
time we do one of these projects like
the idea that we had at the beginning
and the end are often super different
and you have to really just be putting
in the energy every day to think about
it. Okay, are we today still doing the
right thing?
Are the are the changes due to like
misassessment of what the AI can cannot
do? Is this what the user might want to
use it? I guess what what do you feel
drives the more substantial evolution
versus authoring?
Yeah, yeah. It comes from multiple
places. Yeah, one is definitely what the
AI can and cannot do and then actually
morphing the experience to what the AI
does well to
the thing you discover that it does
well.
I think that's pretty important. Another
big element is there's no product
paradigms really around it. There's a
few things. We have the AI chat concept
now. There's a few concepts now, but
there's just not that much. So, you have
to invent things and then when you have
people actually using them, you can
easily discover a lot of things like the
user wasn't use this
the way I expected. So, yeah, just
there's a lot of uncertainty around just
like inventing the product concept. It's
such a fuzzy weird technology. For any
given goal, if you think of all right, I
want to build this feature for this
goal, I can think of 10 different ways
to do it. You have to navigate that.
Another big one is discovering an ideal
feature. I think doesn't require people
to change their habits.
It's just embedded in their existing
habits.
That's that's really great if you can
get that. Otherwise, you have this this
double challenge of in in a industry to
make your thing work. You have to
actually
get people into your flow. It is
particularly hard for us cuz Notion
already does so many different things.
So, yeah, that's a really big one and
it's not always obvious at the
beginning.
So, yeah, I was yeah, I was saying like
general umbrella there is like just a
lot of iteration speed and capable of
dealing with that uncertainty. On the
kind of modeling ML side, I would say
one of the biggest predictors of success
is just like how often do they touch
reality? Like how often do they like try
that idea and run that experiment and
then they kind of loop on that because
it's such a weird technology like it has
to be so empirically driven.
You can have an idea and you're not
going to get anywhere unless you try it
and you should try it really quickly and
then move on to the next idea. Not just
on the project level but you know on a
day-to-day level of just like different
ways to solve each problem. So yeah, the
really key thing there is just like they
have to just be able to just
really quickly empirically iterate.
Yeah.
And if you don't do that it's not going
to work.
It's a great advice and I think what I
find really interesting is that it
actually is very grounded in product.
None of the skills you mentioned are
hey, it'll be useful if they have a
master's in machine learning or in
general kind of mileage with kind of Do
you I I relate to that and I don't like
I come from software development from
product. Also, it's hard to find good
software engineers that also happen to
have an ML background. So is that an
advantage to that? But do you find those
are advantageous like when you see
someone with a resume or when you look
at the people in your team that feel
like they're the best
or have been the best at adapting to it?
Does a machine learning background help?
Yeah, I think not necessarily.
It's funny. I'm not sure. I mean, we
definitely have some really great uh
folks on the team that have an ML
background. I've definitely met people
where they had an ML background but it
felt like it it was actually harming
them especially the background is like
from the pre-language model era.
Yeah, the symbolic AI.
Yeah, it's just a different You can
easily get trapped into some old ways of
thinking. A lot of the concepts do still
apply and it and it is helpful to apply
those but I don't think I look for that
as like
one of the primary things. In fact, I
actually like it if someone has a strong
ML background, I have to suss out like
like how locked in are they to the to
the previous paradigm. But it Yeah, I
will say that if you have a strong ML
background and you're into the new tech
and a strong open-mindedness, then it
can be a huge strength.
Yeah, that's a great combination for it
then. So I I guess maybe one of the
question on the dev side of it. How uh
strongly did you adopt the notion not
just in the AI team, the use of AI in
development? Any Maybe starting with
you. Do you use any of the cursor or the
AI test generations or docs whatever?
What what's your tool of choice if any
in the AI dev space?
Yeah, these days I'm using
cursor. It's really good. I in
particular I really like their auto
complete model. It's just extremely good
that it it can actually produce
arbitrary edits around the code and I
have often found myself tab tapping. I
think there's a meme on
Twitter I saw a few weeks ago. It was
just like the new engineer experience is
just like dump. That's pretty funny.
Yeah, I think yeah, cursor is really
great. I just yeah, I use like Claude or
I chat GPT. More Claude for coding these
days.
Just in the chat to ideate and the
Yeah, yeah, and yeah, I code for me.
And what about the rest of the team? Are
the team Is there a standard when you
think about Notion as an organization?
Have you pushed to Do you push people to
use it? Did you try to standardize on
anything?
Yeah, we definitely do try to push
people to use the tools we think are
most productive. We have most engineers
using cursor now. And then we're
experimenting with We're doing like like
proof of concepts with a bunch of
startups doing various things. I
wouldn't say there's anything crazy
successful to call out there.
Yeah, there's a lot of startups working
on just like coding agent
type things and yeah, I think we're
working on a few like for us some
refactoring projects and yeah, I would
say nothing quite works yet still. I was
actually just playing with Devin again.
I
I'll try Devin every couple months cuz
they're always improving and it's
actually gotten a lot better. It still
didn't do the my favorite eval example.
Yeah, I'm curious now. What's your
favorite eval example? Is it just that
specific code base?
It's an app. Yeah, so it's a
it's pretty simple app, but it touches
all the pieces that I think are
interesting. So, like it's a calorie
tracking app.
All it is is it's a table of with the
food and the amount of calories and then
there's an input and you can just type
whatever you want and then it's supposed
to extract out each food item and and
and the cars added to the table. So, it
involves a database, a back end, a front
end, and then it also has to write a
prompt and and and call into a language
model to do the extraction.
And last time I tried, it actually did
get the initial version, and then I
asked for just one small feature change,
and then it didn't work from there. So,
they've made huge improvements, and it's
like super impressive. But, yeah, I I
feel like we're not quite there yet
still.
Yeah. I wanted to shift gears a little
bit and talk a bit about trust in AI.
And then, maybe we do come back a little
bit to this like future of both
development and the Notion AI itself.
I think in AI, a lot of the challenge
with sort of users is learning and
knowing what to do, what can they do
with that sort of empty chat box or
actions as you pointed out, like
learning new workflows is also quite
hard. But, I think another challenge is
trust. You're putting something in, how
do you A simple example of I don't know
if it hallucinated something, but also
like how do you know if it succeeded in
a thing or if the answer is correct.
Like, it could hallucinate, but it could
also just be wrong. And that's How do
you think about
trust in Notion AI? Is there anything
you've learned around helping users
figure out when can they trust an answer
in Q&A more than elsewhere or uh you
know, and and again, some of it is
true or legit, your product did or
didn't work. But, also some of it is
it's just user adaptation and learning
new skills.
How do you think about that?
Yeah.
Yeah, that's something we think about a
lot. I would say, the most obvious tools
are one,
if the AI is taking an action, have the
user confirm that and be able to see
in a nicely visualized way what is the
action being performed. I think that's
just like a really key thing. So, even
for our original AI writing, the first
product that that we came out with, it
never just edits your doc. It's always
producing a diff, and then you preview
the diff, and you can accept it or
cancel. And if you want both, you can
there's like a insert below button. And
then, you can but you can side step a
lot of those problems just by letting
users visualize
eventually. So, the user decides. You
just prompt them to
I think that's that's the most critical
tool and that's extremely useful. It
kind of side steps a lot of it. Just let
the user decide if it if they like it or
not. And it especially makes sense for
the writing task cuz it's a fuzzy task.
Like it might it might have partially
done it right and that's still useful.
But it's not something you'd want to
like immediately send an email about.
And then you mentioned Q&A. I think
yeah, super important thing there is
just citations.
And I visualize those in a good way so
it's grounded and then and
And how often do people use those? Do
people when you look at the at the
stats, do people actually go off and
click those links and make sure
that you didn't make it up or is it
more, "Hey, it's actually needed cuz we
get it wrong often enough that we
actually still want users to correct
us." Or is it typically
"Hey, it's just like for the warm and
fuzzy, but we're pretty good at this."
People click the citations quite a bit.
I've I think it's more than like a web
search tool because you actually might
want to go see more information.
It is like an internal doc that somebody
wrote. But I would say, yeah, it really
depends on the nature of of the
question. There's a class of questions
where, you know, they I can just really
robustly answer them.
Some kind of factual question. Do we
have President's Day off or something?
Yeah, it's going to if it's written
somewhere, it's going to figure that
out. It's going to cite it. But there's
not much chance of it like like messing
up on that. And then if you see that you
see that answer, yes, we have it off and
then here's the page and it says 2024
benefits. And the user's not going to
click through on that probably.
But yeah, Q&A at the limit is an
arbitrarily hard task. People ask and
especially when we get to connectors
like pulling from many sources, people
can ask a kind of complicated One thing
we're working on right now that I'm
really excited about is a GitHub
connector so we can actually see your
code in your PRs. And that's really fun
because a non-technical person can ask a
technical question
and then you get this really interesting
answer where it's like weaving together
something from the code, something from
Slack that somebody said and then
something from some Notion docs or tasks
that that somebody wrote. And then
yeah, it's doing a much harder task at
that point. Weaving together the
information from multiple sources, and
then there's
many potentials for it to make reasoning
mistakes. It might be conflating two
things that are actually similar.
How do you handle those situations then?
Like you're representing an answer. Is
there an element of like confidence or
something like that? Have you considered
adding that to the product? Okay, I'm
70%
sure this is right.
Yeah, yeah.
We do definitely prompt it about that. I
think that's pretty important. We want
the model with So, mostly using
language. We don't have like an
indicator. I think you can go a pretty
long way
using language to telling it that it
needs to communicate uncertainty when
it's there. And the models are getting
pretty decent at doing that.
And would it sometimes say it doesn't
know?
Yeah, definitely. Yeah, yeah, if it's
not there, yeah, it doesn't know. Yeah,
we wanted Yeah, that's part of the
prompt, too. We want it to have
reasonably high bar.
A bit of a side question on it, but like
how big do the prompts get? Like all of
that. So, the system prompt.
Pretty big. We're definitely pushing the
limits, especially the Q&A prompt,
definitely. Also the writing prompts.
We're definitely pushing the limits of
what the models can do, especially
because we want it to work in all the
cases, right? And so, over time, we've
incorporated all these interesting
corner cases people find that we don't
want to regress on. Yeah, I feel like
we're maxing out the prompt. Not in
terms of the actual context length, but
in the context length have gotten pretty
long pretty long, but I think in terms
of the model's ability to actually
attend over complex instructions. The
system instructions are quite long and
there's many examples.
And then also there's the actual user
task, which can have a lot of additional
context. I often feel like after a few
like maybe weeks of iteration or
something and like and they find all the
regressions, it can actually be pretty
hard more beyond that.
So, we often will find cases where it's
okay. The engineers working on it,
they'll add it to the system prompt. In
this case,
don't do this or something. But then it
just doesn't work. There's too much
going on already.
instructions, yeah. I guess like humans,
if you kind of give me too many
instructions, eventually I will I might
technically remember it, but won't pull
it up at the right time.
Yeah. Yeah, so we often have to just
like prioritize and just be like, all
right, this case, maybe the only way to
solve it is just for it to attend over
that instruction somehow, and it's just
not working, so that at that point,
unless we have some more creative idea,
we have to wait.
And do you ever engage users and have
you considered doing so in the thought
process of hey, to answer this Q&A, I
pulled information from these
seven locations and I've blended them
together and get user feedback on it.
Maybe I'll broaden even that question,
which is like Notion is a very powerful
tool and it has probably a lot of
regular users, but it also has some
pretty real power users who can really
squeeze a lot more out of the product
because they know how to make the most
of it. Is there a power user of Notion
AI?
Yeah, yeah. So, for Notion we think a
lot about like primitives or building
blocks. Our goal as a company
is to
try to break the pattern of these like
rigid vertical SaaS
tools and instead reconstruct them from
their underlying primitives and allow
users to make their own custom software.
So, things like a relational database or
a table view or different blocks for
that page. I think of AI as another
primitive in the toolbox that you do
really useful automations on top.
So, yeah, we have AI primitive concepts.
So, the writing that AI autofill is a
great example. That's a primitive where
you can write a custom prompt and then
you can do whatever you want. And then
our power users basically are writing
these really long complex prompts to do
something crazy. And then the way that
has impact for us is then their complex
prompt gets packaged as a Notion
template, which then can be distributed
to other people.
Yeah, interesting. So, I guess the
answer is taking two things. One is it's
not a Notion AI power user, it's a
Notion power user and AI is part of
their kind of toolkit now that they have
under the primitives they can understand
and they can make the most. And then two
is that yeah, within Notion AI, you're
looking for capabilities to make
available to those users when they
really want to double down and prompts
are the core version of it. Have any of
these prompts eventually make it back to
the product of hey, these users figured
these things out with the proper
permission?
I think so. Yeah, we've definitely
several times
had in like beta testing a feature. We
like for example for the writing
a
a writing product, the way it works is
is we have these kind of pre-designed
prompts that we control. And there were
definitely several examples of like
people saying, "Hey, I want to do this.
It's not quite working." And then we
make the prompt. And then we'll optimize
it like like much more than they could.
Yeah. One more question on the trust
side. A lot of the conversations I've
had here on the podcast came down to
this kind of a garbage in garbage out
type reality where or maybe indeed in
support cases like in Intercom if your
knowledge base is incorrect, then your
support bot will give incorrect answers
because it's relying on that
information. On it or talking to Jason
or when we're at pool side, talked a
little bit about how do you overcome bad
coding practices that you might have in
the code and sniff those out. I imagine
within an organization that has enough
maturity with Notion, you're going to
have a lot of documents that are out of
date. They no longer represent kind of
reality or truth. How do you think about
I don't know if it's ranking or
identifying the better, the correct
data, the good data from the bad one?
Yeah. Yeah, that's extremely important.
That works on a lot. Yeah, very similar
to code. People often don't update the
old thing. It's probably even worse than
code. Knowledge bases are often like
like very neglected.
Yeah, I I you almost touched on it.
Yeah, I think there's two steps where
this can happen where it solves this
problem. One is in like some kind of
ranking or filtering step. We definitely
do a lot there. We want to make sure
that we're ranking the the highest
confidence documents using all the
signals that we can like like how
recently was the document edited. Is it
maybe where is it located? Is it
connected to other documents? Who wrote
it? We try to use all these like signals
and you can get quite far with that.
Even just when the document was last
edited or viewed is it like very
powerful signal. And then yeah, then the
second step is
giving it all to the model and having it
decide. And the models have gotten like
much better at that. I think yeah, our
case is different than like the Intercom
case cuz the Intercom case you're
sending this message to a customer
autonomously. So, that's pretty high
stakes.
I think for our
Q&A product, it's a bit lower stakes.
It's all internal information. And then
we're
users, yeah.
Yeah, our prompt is more about just like
presenting to you all the relevant
information in a really distilled,
actionable way. And so, if there's like
multiple sources
that say conflicting things,
we want our answer to just say that.
Whereas in the intercom case, you
probably wouldn't want that. So, it's a
bit of a different
No, you'd have to conclude what is the
answer you have to relate to the user.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah, we
Yeah, if it says if one document said
the product is shipping this month and
one says the other month, we uh the
answer should just say both. Like it
just says, "In the most recent document,
it says this, but in this document, it
said that." And that's really useful for
people.
Yeah.
And I guess too, how when you say you
give it all to the LLM, that includes
then the metadata of probably obviously
like dates the documents were written
and things like that. But is does it
cope with more metadata as well with
things like
uh view like visit counts and I don't
know, like organizational chart of like
seniority if that's more of an authority
or like affinity to a domain or do you
end up going down those routes and are
those impactful?
Yeah, I I would say that yeah, like I'm
a bit less bullish on like showing it
some kind of like rank score or
something like that. I don't think it'll
be able to reason that well over that,
but
I don't know. I think of it like if you
were showing a person a stack of
documents and you had this and give them
all day to figure out like what's the
answer,
what would you give them? Like when the
document was last edited, for example,
feels like a great one, right? Cuz
that's it it it's a very transparent
signal.
And it's actually useful for the answer
itself. Like the model will actually
often
directly use that information in the
answer. It will say, "In this document
was edited a month ago or something like
that." But yeah, I would say, yeah, I
think it it's I'm a little bit I'd be
wary of showing it like non-transparent
like black boxy type information cuz you
could easily steer them in the wrong
direction. If the answer is wrong, but
somehow your system produced affinity
score 0.9 or or or whatever and the
model use that information. Yeah, that's
I don't think that's going to work very
well.
Yeah, I heard you say on another podcast
that you're better off trying to stay
close to the way the model was trained
to the data that the model might have
seen, right? And and I guess that aligns
with date stamps is probably something
the models saw a lot in their training
data. Uh view counts is probably not
something that was uh frequently there.
Yeah, especially any kind of like novel
score that they they produce things that
are never seen before.
Yeah.
So let's maybe for for the last section
here talk a little bit about being
ambitious, which I heard you refer to of
you need to be when you think about AI.
You need to be ambitious around where
it's headed and plan for it. And so let
me start by by asking a bit of a meta
question and then we'll
maybe I try to get a bit of a bit of a
glimpse into your ambition. With AI you
when you build an AI solution have this
duality of on one hand you want to fit
into the current flow as you pointed out
here as well because users don't really
know what they want and how to use this.
So you have to fit into their current
realities and you also want to be
ambitious. You want to think about uh
the future and something that's entirely
different, but you think when you stop
and think about it from first principles
that there might be a better way to do
it. I guess how do you think about the
two and how do you prioritize
between these two tracks as you build
the AI capabilities?
So just to understand it's like you're
asking about incrementally changing
existing behaviors and
Yeah, so let me maybe let me reiterate a
bit. So I have this mental model that
thinks about the level of change and the
level of trust that you need in any AI
solution and the solutions that get the
most adoption today are the ones that
require little change and little trust.
So there are things that are very easily
achievable and verifiable and they are
therefore easy to adopt on it, but they
also have a bit of a local maxima
because they work within the workflow.
They don't change anything around it.
The solutions presumably, that have the
top potential of it are ones that assume
you have high trust, and so you allow
autonomous actions and and the likes,
and you're willing to adapt to the way
you work to be able to make the most out
of the
new capabilities of it, but those are
hard to adopt because
you don't really have that trust, and
you haven't changed. And so, that's a as
you pointed out, a double ask of the
user. But eventually, I guess my theory
or kind of my perspective here is that
it is a local maximum if you limit
yourself to existing workflows. So, you
have to think a little bit about the
head. So, I guess what I'm asking is one
is do you agree? My this is just theory.
That's not at all proven. And then two
is like how do you think about the two?
I'm sure you have a lot of like
longer-term thoughts about where this is
all headed. Are those just basically
they go into the parking lot, or do you
try to build them into the product in in
some wilder bets that you do in
parallel?
Yeah, I don't think those things need to
be separate necessarily. I think there's
Yeah, when I'm thinking about a
a new product, I have two
considerations. One is what is the
capability and the value being created,
and does it actually work? And then
there's a second one around like how do
you onboard people into it and expose
them to it? And I think if you're clever
about it, you can be both familiar and
in their workflow and also giving a new
capability, even an autonomous one. Like
in you should be able to connect it to
something they're already doing,
and also propose a new behavior, and
then incrementally get them into the
more autonomous way. Yeah, I think if
you cleverly design it, like it it
doesn't feel like a fundamental
correlation, it just feels like it
happens to be correlated in that way,
but if you're clever about it, it's
doesn't need to be. And I think
the best thing the best example is
probably just the the code auto
complete. So, originally Co-pilot and
then like Cursor's one is extremely
good. It's actually doing quite a bit
for you and like scaling it up
uh scaling up in what it does for you.
And then, yeah, I think you can
ambiently show people a new experience
in something that they're already doing.
That's the ideal.
Yeah, yeah, to get the adoption. Yeah, I
get it. I've got all sorts of thoughts
about the code base on it because I do
think there's something about sort of
moving out of editing the code even if
you can edit the code much better to a
different source of truth. A different
different conversation. But well said
around making it the journey and making
it be incremental steps that lead the
user to that destination. So I guess
with that, what is the future for Notion
AI? If you could overcome and educate
everybody or whatever, walk them through
this path over a bunch of years, what do
you envision as the destination for
Notion AI or how would it transform
Notion?
I would say the North Star for me for AI
is basically can you automate all the
things that people don't want to be
doing, right? All the cumbersome tedious
tasks that that people do every day. And
ultimately lift humans up into a higher
level of abstraction where where they're
doing like higher leverage, more
fulfilling activities. To me that's like
the North Star in what's possible with
AI. For Notion, I think about we're
basically like a a knowledge work
system, right? And people do all kinds
of different knowledge work tasks on it.
You might be an engineer managing your
team's knowledge base and the tasks and
and the projects maybe like a product
manager doing your product road map and
giving updates. You might be like a
sales leader making like a like a custom
CRM. And so much of what people do in
Notion is these tedious tasks, right?
Notion's core important concept is the
database, like a relational database and
a lot of what people are doing is
essentially like manual data entry into
the database, right?
Uh
manually reading and writing to it.
There's a huge opportunity there, but I
see basically let's lift up one level of
abstraction and these tools like a
database should become like an
implementation detail
and the AI is or some workflow that
involves AI
should be automating all these tedious
steps.
And the human should be uplifted to be
more like observing the final outputs
and steering them
and figuring out what like high-level
tasks are are more important to us.
And is it a a curation exercise if you
can reliably
extract information from the original
source, whatever listen to a
conversation and capture it, or indeed
with your connectors pick it up from
other systems, and you put them into
Notion,
then Notion as a knowledge base,
it it is it about it being a curated
knowledge base because humans have
chosen what goes in and what doesn't go
in or verified it in the process?
Yeah.
As opposed to just having a firehose
access at any time.
Yeah, in the in the pre-AI world, like
for any use case, Notion's like the
repository for it and and the way that
you read and write to it. I think in the
AI world, it's also like the host for
the workflow that actually
directly does that that job to be done
that that the data is trying to
accomplish. For example, let's say
you're an engineering team, one of the
things that an engineering teams do is
they manage their tasks, incoming bugs,
triage them, figure out which bugs are
important, which ones are going to work
on this week.
When they're finished, maybe you want to
like notify the right people,
maybe tell the customer that it it was
fixed.
That whole end-to-end workflow should be
automated. And then the level of
abstraction of the engineer working on
that is thinking less about this is
ticket that came in, is it a clear bug,
do I need repro steps, should I send it
back to the customer? And the level of
abstraction is like a little bit higher
on more of the strategy of which let's
encode into the system
which classes of bugs are most important
for us to fix. So, when it's something
like high priority, it should be flagged
to us.
And when it's something low priority, it
should be backlogged.
And then the AI is actually making those
micro decisions and managing the
database for you.
And I guess how do you think about
evolution of Notion? There might be like
a lot of the tedious data entry work
done in Notion, but Notion is also like
really good at that, or rather it's a
much more delightful experience to enter
that data into Notion than it is into
other tools, and I dare say that's one
of the competitive advantages of notion
compared to some tools. And so, if
that's the case, is there like a
strategy change that you have to apply
to say, "Hey, you know, of course we'll
keep maintaining this, but
it's actually more important now, for
instance, to invest in workflows than it
is to in I might be getting into secret
sauce material over here, so
I think it's still both important. So,
the limit, let's say for the engineering
task triage use case that I just talked
about, at the limit, you could just ask
like a coding agent, "Make this entire
thing for me." And it will make like a
Postgres database. And then like
Postgres database for your tasks, and
then it will go connect to the Zendesk
API and input them, right? Like that
will work at the limit. It doesn't quite
work now, but I think in that world,
though,
you still want a convenient
data container and a permission model
that is end-user
accessible. That I think that would
still be like much preferred. I don't
want my tasks to be in some like
Postgres database with a one-off custom
UI that was built on top of it. And who
has access to it? And have I verified
that? Is it also building me a whole
permission model where I can see who has
access? And is it tested? And right? So,
I still think that world is really
important, even when the AI is
automating 90% of the workflow,
you still want to maybe
go in and see the current task list and
go look at the backlog and maybe able to
see one that that shouldn't have been
backlogged and then go add it to the
current sprint or whatever it is. And
so, that that's all really important. I
just think of it more like
the balance will shift a bit more to the
workflows, but this like highly
user-accessible data container is still
extremely important. We're going to
I think of it like, yeah, keep investing
in that and that's the foundation and
then the workflows are like reducing the
tedious work.
Yeah, and additionally, I absolutely
relate to that. Right? I often times say
that you don't want to be in the place
in which when you ask the LLM to create
an LLM to create a Tic-Tac-Toe game for
you, it will have to create an operating
system. Like, you want to be able to
build on reusable components that are
good.
You want shared jargon between different
users. You want to go from one company
to the other and be able to see familiar
interfaces especially amidst things that
are not necessarily true or not. They're
just taste. They're just preference. But
at least you can create commonalities
and norms. So
Right.
And I think in the in the category of
knowledge work like I think Notion is
conveniently made like a really good
data container for that. What do you
need for knowledge work? You need a
database definitely, multiple databases
related to each other. And you want like
unstructured documents as well. And then
you want them all wrapped up in a
container that's that's convenient for
users and for the AI. And with a clear
permission model so that we can trust
what the AI is access to read or write
to.
Yeah. Yeah, makes a lot of sense. So I
guess maybe one last question is what is
your wish list in terms of the future of
development? So when you think about
AI-powered software development, what's
if you cast your eyes to the future,
what would you like to have?
Yeah. I would love to I guess similarly
to the knowledge work thing like I think
of it as just yeah successive layers of
abstraction of abstracting away tedious
work and getting me into higher level
modes of operating. Auto complete is
like the most basic layer.
And with the new like cursor one, it
took me from auto completing this one
line to actually it can do like
semi-complicated refactor just by
tapping through the document. And then
if you actually like chat with the AI,
you can ask a function
basically or maybe write some tests for
me. And then yeah, just like successive
layers of abstraction. Can it do the
micro task that I'm trying to do right
now? That's like a 30-minute task. Can
it actually
design and spec this entire part of the
code and write all the tests and
implement it. I would love for my level
of abstraction to be more like a
technical product manager than a coder
at some point.
Right.
Right. Where all I'm doing is just
getting rigorous about what the
requirements are and roughly how it
should work. And then yeah, letting it
figure out like how to actually
implement it and how to test it and
prove to me that what it wrote actually
works. And then when when I have a
feature request, I can just communicate
that in some clear way.
I that would be incredible. I think
yeah, not quite there yet but that
sounds good.
Yeah. Yeah, we're one of those working
on it. We'll get back to you on that.
year.
Yeah, sounds good.
Simon, thanks for all the other insights
and the sharing here. It was a pleasure
having you on the podcast.
Yeah, it was super fun. Thanks for
having me.
And thanks everyone for tuning in. I
hope you join us for the next one.
Thanks for tuning in. Join us next time
on the AI Native Dev, brought to you by
Tesseract.